[Music]
previously I've talked about chlorella's
potential benefits for preserving the
immune function of athletes and
improving some cardiovascular risk
factors such as dropping blood pressures
by a few points or lowering LDL
cholesterol about eight points remember
that green eggs and ham study where
taking chlorella with eggs appeared to
blunt the rise in cholesterol it may
help detoxify some dietary cholesterol
but what about the toxins found
contaminating many algae supplements
blue green algae like AFA can make their
own toxins but even if the green algae
chlorella can't when chlorella is
skimmed off the ponds the presence of
other algae in microorganisms is
unavoidable and compose a hazard when
you actually look at commercial algae
supplements under a microscope the
provided labels are usually inaccurate
as factual contents usually do not match
they may be contaminated with fungus
other algae and bacteria and it seems
that contamination was more frequent in
the organic versus conventional products
one product advertised as 100% organic
chlorella contain both liver toxins and
neurotoxins I've talked about a case
report of apparent chlorella induced
psychosis there's also been a case of
kidney damage reported as well as an
apparent chlorella induced drop in
platelet count some reactions are hard
to miss like a whole body rash or nausea
headache disiness fatigue abdominal pain
and general weakness that rapidly
resolved after stopping in these cases
though it was a mixed algae product even
without contamination if you cultivate
pure chlorella it can still
significantly induce DNA damage in human
cells yeah but those are all cells in a
Petri dish yes but they were colon
lining cells so cells presumably exposed
directly to chlorella when you eat it
though chlorella has been marketed for
quote quote detoxification it can be
contaminated with toxin producing algae
and end up exceeding safety limits for
more irony chlorella can sometimes be
contaminated in a good way chlorella
species can't make vitamin B12 but they
may mix with B12 synthesizing bacteria
such that if you give chlorella to some
vegetarians and vegans with a suspected
vitamin B12 deficiency most seem to get
a little Improvement in their B12 status
but after 2 months of supplement they
were still on average deficient note
that chlorella is not considered to be a
reliable sufficient source of vitamin
B12 the same with spirulina which was
once thought to contain B12 but it's
actually mostly pseudo B12 a form of B12
unusable by humans and therefore not a
suitable B12 Source what about spiring
as a source of
toxins I'll address just that question
next
[Music]